[Applause]
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
door / software welcome listeners to a
new episode of se radio my name is
Johannes and I'm sitting here with
Rebecca Parsons who is CTO at
ThoughtWorks where I could incidentally
also work she before working for Horace
she was an assistant professor at the
University of Central Florida
she earned a PhD in computer science
from the Rice University today she is
also chair of the agile Alliance and has
over 20 years of experience in
application development in industry
ranging from telecommunication to
emergent Internet services she has also
been already on the show together with
Martin Fowler on episode 182 about
domain-specific languages so welcome
back to su radio very much yeah and
you're actually the first guest we
invited because some of our listeners
said I wonder really here Rebecca
Parsons I don't know that's that's why
we picked you up so I hope we make our
listeners happy with that it's the only
thing you want to add to yourself well
about the only thing I would add is is I
have also done a significant amount of
work recently with UNICEF in Uganda I
did my sabbatical there they have a sort
of informal Fellows Program where you
can go spend some time working with
their technology teams and that was
actually quite an experience living for
three months in Uganda after after this
kind of career with that works quite a
change of pace yes yes I can imagine
I guess we're gonna link in the show
notes to this program maybe someone
wants to find out more about it so today
we are talking about evolutionary energy
architecture
that's actually a topic where you talk
about we already had episode 166 on
living architecture
which is a similar topic so you might
find one or the other concept here again
but it's an it's an interesting enough
topic that we thought we might do
another show was another perspective on
it so let me start with a slightly odd
question to a city Oh Rebecca are you an
architect or are you a developer well I
I'm both actually I do think that there
are perspectives of the role of
architect that are distinct from the
role of of a developer when you when
you're a developer your focus is on the
specific code that you're writing the
system that you're developing how it
satisfies the business requirements and
how it satisfies the technical
requirements sometimes called the
non-functional requirements which I
always think is bizarre how can it not
be functional but it's you know those
things that don't directly contribute to
solving the business problem where as
part of an architect's responsibility is
to step back a little bit and set that
in context and there are many different
kinds of architects there are technical
architects security architects data
architects software architects
Enterprise architects and all of them
have a little bit different focus but
you do have to think differently about
what it is that you're doing if you're
looking at things in the context of say
as an Enterprise Architect you you look
at one particular product or software
asset in the context of the entire suite
of enterprise assets and how do those
things fit together ok so is an
architect rather a person or is it a
role I I fit in I consider it a role or
at least a nice umbrella for a set of
activities there are organizations that
are small enough where developers and
architects can easily be the same person
because the scope of what you're looking
at is small enough that one person can
keep it all in their head and you start
to think of some of the massive
enterprises that that exist one person
can't keep the minutiae of all of those
systems as well as how all everything
fits together and so then you tend to
see more more separation of
responsibilities but it really is a role
in a set of tasks yeah when I when I
hear you talking I have the
oppression there is also kind of a a
layering of architecture maybe even a
hierarchy of architect someone who has
the big picture of the whole company and
someone who's directly involved with the
the developers team well there there are
there are a layer of tasks and you you
characterized it correctly and it has
more to do with the scope of what you're
concerned with the overall enterprise
architect their scope is the entire
enterprise and in fact it might
encompass the IT assets of even some of
their suppliers or their customers if
you're a security architect or a data
architect your scope is is much more
narrow because you're focused on a
particular concern you have a
cross-cutting Yakka textural rather than
an overreaching okay before we dive
deeper into that there is a famous quote
from Martin Fowler saying architecture
is the stuff that's hard to change
so is evolutional architecture the way
to make the stuff that's hard to change
easier to change easier but not easy and
and that that really is an important
distinction one of the things about
architecture and the way it's been
approached in the past is there there's
almost a a speculation about how things
are going to be in the future what uses
people are going to want to put my
customer data to and the architects
responsibility was almost to predict the
future and try to say ok this is how
people are going to want to use this
therefore I will proactively develop
things that will address a future need
what evolutionary architecture is time
trying to get across is predicting the
future is hard and getting harder and so
rather than rely on guessing right about
what's going to happen in the future you
set up your systems so that it is easier
to move in whatever direction the future
brings so when you when you want to set
up a system to be evolved what what is
the strategy for doing that how do you
know where you want to go well there are
a couple of things and this is this is
why I distinguish between emergent and
evolutionary and this is a this is a
debate I've had with with several
thought workers Neil Ford and Martin
Fowler are some of them Neal speaks a
lot about emergent design and people
will often talk about architecture as an
emergent architecture and I like to
focus on the evolutionary architecture
because part of that is there is a sense
of what is right there is a sense of
good a fitness function and if you think
about genetic algorithms evolutionary
computation you have a notion of a
fitness function this is my goal and
that Fitness function characterizes my
goal in the case of architecture that
has to do a lot with what are the
characteristics of the architecture that
you're looking for if you have a lot of
personally identifiable information
credit card numbers health information
something like that you're going to have
a much greater concern for security than
if this is a sandwich ordering system
and I really am not terribly concerned
if people know that I always order an
excel at sandwich so the the needs for
data security are much different in that
application the different performance
requirements for different kinds of
systems do I need to worry about load do
I need to worry about communication you
know is there are there a lot of
messages or not too many all of those
different things that we talked about
from the perspective of architecture the
LEDs as we often refer to them how I how
I set the dials if you will on my
concern for those different LEDs start
to give me the characteristics that I'm
looking for in an architecture these are
the things that I want to maintain and I
use that fitness function as a way of
evaluating the different decisions I'm
making along the way am i keeping myself
true to what it is that I'm trying to
achieve am i moving things in the right
direction because I have this goal it's
not just do whatever I have a goal of
satisfying these these illa T's and I'm
trying to move the architecture in that
direction not get there immediately
because I don't know what the path needs
to look like but as long as I know this
is my goal and I would need to be able
to justify whatever decisions I make
from the perspective of that fitness
function that what constitutes good for
my architects
how would a fitness function let's say
for Twitter look and how would the
Fitness function for the Soderbergh's
website look well a Twitter obviously
has a different volume profile Twitter
has to worry much more about burst
activity so all of a sudden something
happens in the world and you've got a
mass of you know thousands or millions
of retweets
whereas the thoughtworks website you're
probably going to have less focused
traffic a different load profile you're
less likely to get you know the enormous
burst yeah even when something goes
seriously viral that's not going to be
the same thing as if you know if there's
some major natural disaster or a new war
breaks out or some other activity where
the entire world regardless of your
industry regardless of your job all of
the sudden is taking to Twitter that
kind of load profile is not something
that is going to happen on an IT
companies website and so you you are
looking at those different kinds of
kinds of activities different kinds of
load profiles Twitter knows a lot about
who I'm connected to who I'm following
so again there's different kinds of
information so how they look at
protecting data is going to be different
than how a more content focused website
because there's interaction the Twitter
needs to know about so their performance
characteristics their security there are
many things about how that site works
that that are different and they were
going to result in a different fitness
function if you will for Twitter versus
our website so so Twitter will have as
part of the fitness function probably
stronger ability to react to suddenly
higher traffic than the Salt Works
website has because most of our content
is probably static and can be cached yes
yes okay let's take a little bit more a
look into the terms
you said emergent design and
evolutionary architecture can you
decompose these are those four terms for
me a little bit okay well let's start
with design versus architecture because
that really is a continuum when we talk
about
software architecture part of what we're
talking about is how am i decomposing my
application to into various small C
components so I'm not talking
component-based architecture but
component is a nice handy word for a for
a blob of functionality probably in
class and a few helper classes or
something like yes yes and so design is
actually talking a lot about that
lower-level structure but it starts to
move up a continuum where you might
start to say okay how am I going to have
my inventory system correspond with my
ordering system or my logistics system
because that too is an architectural
decision your your granularity of
components of that case though might
might be much larger so there there is
definitely continuum going from design
into architecture but then there are a
lot of concerns that you have in
architecture like the LEDs that we've
talked about your technical stack
decisions data lifecycle decisions which
are really more architectural rather
than the design so you do have a
continuum there there's a gray area in
the middle and would you say you're
doing you know a software designer
software architecture but really the
important part of architecture is you
were looking at things that are in a
broader context when you're talking
about software design it is much more at
the code level you're worried about how
code components are behaving what they
look like yeah so architecture is more
and reflected like for instance UML
diagram is the standard case some some
people fear and while design is focused
like on the line of code or on the unit
of code I would say that's that's that's
one way of thinking about it yes use you
certainly rarely when you're talking
about architecture are concerned with a
specific line of code but there are
things past there are lots of things
implied by a UML diagram that aren't
consistent with with necessarily my view
of of architecture but you do often have
diagrams that you're if you're trying to
think for example of how information
flows through an enterprise you might
imagine that as as boxes and lines
flowing through to
try to see how do these different
systems relate to each other and you
won't see any code there even though
somewhere down in the in the bowels of
the system yes there there are code
there are lines of code that implement
whatever that communication is yeah all
right so let's let's go to emergent and
evolutionary the distinction to some
extent is that you have a much more
complex version of what constitutes your
goal or goodness in an evolutionary
system there is a field it's called
emergent computation and when you look
at things like neural networks it's some
of the games of life and thus the
simulation of of ant colonies and such
you see what is called emergent behavior
and you have very simple interactions
between these entities and behaviors
emerges when we talk about emergent
design particularly from the perspective
of agile development you're looking at
okay I want to do the simplest thing
that that will solve the problem that I
have now and then as my system grows as
new requirements come on I'm going to
alter my design because I've got new
requirements coming in and that design
is going to emerge so rather than
sitting up back at the beginning and
saying I know exactly what my object
hierarchy for example will look like
that object hierarchy emerges over time
as these new features come in and you
decide what is the best way to implement
it and you have some very simple
characterizations of what a clean design
looks like you know don't repeat
yourself
all of these those different very simple
design principles but basically your
your idea of good is not necessarily
that context specific you want you want
to clean hierarchy you want separation
of concerns and different kinds of code
are not necessarily going to have that
different a characterization of what
constitutes good code when we talk about
architecture though you know as we just
discussed the performance profile of
Twitter is very different than that of a
Content website I have a lot more
variables in terms of what constitutes
my goal state what constitutes a good
architecture clearly
there there are analogs to clean code
you want to clean architecture you want
to think about you know what is the how
much chatter is between two components
and such but some of them are going to
be very specific the load profile on a
system that only has to handle a hundred
transaction a day how how you think
about your architectural decisions and
what constitutes a good architecture is
going to be very different than then
it's in the Twitter yeah case so you
have you have more variables that are
involved in that decision and you are
trying to again there is still the sense
of you are going to move toward
something and the architecture does
emerge in that sense but it emerges
towards a more specific goal it emerges
- it's a fitness function yes so when
you talk of evolutionary architecture
this means you evolve your architecture
step by step in small steps can you
contrast that with the common practice
of re-architecting your system
re-architecting the system often happens
when something major has changed so
either either new technology is
available that you want to take
advantage of and now I need to rethink
how my system is going to satisfy my my
fitness function in the new context of
this of this new technology stack and it
might be just a simple transfer but
there might be characteristics of this
new technology stack that I want to take
advantage of so there there are aspects
of re architecting a system that are the
same it's not so much whether or not
your rear connecting but it is how much
you decide to think about your end state
at any given point in time so one of the
one of the things that that we often see
a an enterprise decides we are now going
to be a service-oriented enterprise and
I'm going to bring in this this you know
this big tool that is going to do
everything for me and I'm going to
completely reaaargh attacked my system
you know in segunda vez ops align react
okay yes all right
you know I'm stopping the architecture
and
I'm doing the reoccupation and then I
continue building something yes yes yeah
and what part of what we try to do with
evolutionary architecture is rather than
how that start stop the line mentality
how do I move my architecture
incrementally from where I am to where
I'm trying to get to yeah all right so
we ran a drug company and agile is how
we want to build software not only we
but the rest of the world as well and
architecture has kind of a bad
reputation in in this areas because
people talk about become front design
mm-hmm one of the interesting things if
you look at the evolution of agile in in
the beginning it was developers and
everybody said oh sure it's all right
for development team to do that but as a
business analyst I need to specify my
entire problem before I can turn it over
to developers and they can chunk it up
how they want and then testers well how
will not honor that is something unless
it's completely there and we started
learning over time how how you do
incremental testing how you do
incremental analysis database
administrators well of course I have to
know what my entire data model looks
like and all of my performance
characteristics before we can start any
kind of development and so over time
we've been pushing the boundaries of how
we look at doing a particular aspect of
the software development lifecycle in an
agile way agile experience design and
evolutionary architecture is is one way
of talking about how do you think about
architectural problems from the
perspective of Evangel and what one of
the fallacies are the myths if you will
of agile is ok we come in day one and we
just start writing code you don't think
about anything
well sometimes you do start writing code
but that doesn't mean you haven't
thought about anything it it doesn't
mean that there is no design it doesn't
mean that there is no architectural
thinking that goes into things but what
you do is you try to address the
problems as late as you can in the
process and why do you do that because
you know more information and so it's
not that you don't
you any upfront design you don't do any
upfront architecture you just don't do
it all you focus your thinking on what
problems do I need to solve now where is
the greatest risk in my system okay well
that means you might want to prioritize
bringing that forward because if you've
got a major architectural risk that is
going to have a tremendous amount of
influence on how you solve the problem
so if you if you know that your site
related to common use you know that at
some point you get hit by a few million
transactions per minute mm-hmm and
that's something you want to plan before
yes well and there are also things very
often there is some kind of reference
data that might be stored in an old
crusty mainframe somewhere yeah or maybe
a bright shiny mainframe um but it's
still a different a very different
system and if I'm going to need to bring
that data in I'm gonna have to
communicate with that system sometimes
it's very difficult communicating with
those systems and so I'm probably going
to want to prioritize thinking about how
it is I'm going to communicate with that
external system because it's going to be
something that that is more difficult
more risky and therefore I want to bring
bringing that decision forward as long
as I know enough about how it is that
I'm gonna have to communicate what the
communication characteristics are going
to be then I can decide what's the best
approach to communicating without
external system so could could the
evolutional architecture approach be
described by I do some upfront design
every sprint yes
yes right in my mind there is a little
bit the question how would I find the
right balance because so I understand we
want to do some upfront design but we
don't want to do big front upfront
design it's funny by the way that we
call it big upfront design when it's
been a big upfront act yes but that's
that's kind of the term everyone uses
how would it would I balance that what
what are ways to attack that problem
well there's a there there's a principle
that is often discussed in the in the
concept of
of evolution architecture called the
last responsible moment and I very often
get asked that question how do I know
what that last responsible moment is I
know when it's but that that's where the
value of the fitness function comes in
and and definitely one of the very early
things you want to do when thinking
about architecture is what are my
critical architectural features what
does that Fitness function look like
what are the major things that I know
I'm going to have to satisfy and that
are going to be the most influential in
how I decide to approach the problem and
so you look at what what are those
problems and then what what are the
decisions that have to be made and the
decisions that line up with my critical
factors I want to make earlier as long
as I have a sufficient level of
information now it may be you have to
make a particular decision that you
don't have enough information to know
whether it's going to be the right one
and then there are there are software
architecture and software design
patterns that will allow you to protect
yourself from a potential change in the
in that architectural feature there is
an arch of this you know it's not like I
can give you a precise formula that this
decision needs to be made 27.4 days into
development it's never going to be that
that precise but as you as you think
about how does this decision map against
that Fitness function how critical is it
and that allows you to determine what's
the right moment for these these given
decisions when you look at something
like a message queuing system you
probably know fairly early on I'm gonna
need some kind of message queue for this
like for instance if you do medical
applications they tend to have measures
yes but you don't necessarily know do I
need to always ensure that messages are
received by the receiver in exactly the
same order that they were sent or can I
have a bit more flexibility around that
you might not know how persistent the
messages need to be do I need to allow
my receiver to go offline and unpack
online and still be able to access the
messages you know there are all kinds of
characteristics around message queues
and and maybe you don't know the entire
suite of functionality that is is going
to be involved in your message queue you
just know I know at some point I'm going
to be reading and writing messages so
start with a very simple system start
with a very simple tool not a much more
heavyweight one that might have features
that you don't need and then when you
decide ah now I do need guaranteed
ordering I can't use the system that I
was using before I will pick up pick
another one so for each one of these
decisions you need to look at how
difficult is it going to be to change my
mind and how much influence does that
particular decision have on how I'm
going to approach the design of my
application so when I understand it
correct last responsible the monument is
one of your evolutionary architecture
principle because you have a talk called
the principles of evolutionary
architecture yes what are the other
principles well one of the things that
we find an end when you when you look at
thinking about an architecture one of
the things that that gives you a nice
amount of separation and a very clean
architecture is actually to think about
how would I test this system so
architecting for testability is another
one of those principles and what happens
is you end up with abstractions at the
right level it forces you into into a
situation where you have a nice level of
separation of concerns if you think
about testability you end up with with a
good architecture and so this is another
one of the principles because what you
end up with our individual parts of your
ultimate system or application that that
are easy to move around that are easy to
swap out they provides you than a nice
abstraction layer so that that is one of
the principles so the layering of the
tests you apply also gives you a good
separation of concern because if you
have a good unit of tests you also have
a good good
separation it's it's it's not so much
the layering of the test but but your
just your ability to test that and what
one of the things they talk about you
know something's wrong with your system
if all of your tests are does it do this
this is this and this if you can't
succinctly describe what it is the test
is trying to determine you probably have
too much unrelated stuff going on in
there that's true at at you know a unit
test level it's also in in many ways
true even as you go further up into the
acceptance and functional tests if
there's too much stuff abstractly going
on that you can't succinctly describe it
maybe you haven't really thought about
what it is is that test is supposed to
accomplish and how that that chunk of
the system is going to realize that
behavior okay what is another principle
one of the things that is important to
think about from an architectural
perspective is how systems communicate
with each other and there's something
called pastels law where the the
implication for in that for architecture
is I want to be as forgiving as possible
for what I read so I want to be a
tolerant reader so that if if you change
the message that you're sending to me
for whatever reason if it doesn't impact
the things I really need from that
message I shouldn't care yeah so if I
send you addresses and you only care
about postcodes you shouldn't break if I
change the street format exactly exactly
and the flip side of that is is you you
want to be a careful writer you don't
want to put things out in a message that
you aren't comfortable asserting that
I'm always going to put that out there
because as soon as you put that out in a
message somebody might be relying on it
and so those pastels law talks about
this information exchange we often talk
about it in the context of messages but
it's the same thing if you're looking at
trying to pull things out integrating
with a database or you know any other
event source any kind of inbound or
outbound communication the principle it
is still there so you want to think
about how that information
change is going to work so that I can I
can be as tolerant to change as long as
you're not changing what I actually need
from you I shouldn't care yeah so in a
way XML schemas and relational database
schemas are exactly the opposite of
puzzles law if you do full schema
validation yes yes now obviously there's
that there's a little asterisk that you
always have we we don't want to be so
tolerant that we provide a vector for
attack surfaces for you know security
breaches
security breaches and so you want to
make sure that what you're ignoring
isn't a backdoor into your system
somehow but with that caveat you only
want to be looking at the aspect of that
XML message that that you are that you
are specifically concerned with yeah and
how does that help was evolving the
architecture because my part of the
system can evolve as independently as
possible for years and they're there
there's a related technique that we use
on contract testing if I have some kind
of test that documents if you will the
assumptions I am making about your
system and what it's providing to me
what services are behavior I'm expecting
from it I write that into a test and I
give it to you and then I can ignore
everything you're doing yeah I'm sorry
to be a little bit more precise you so
you're right essentially a unit test or
an integration test using a J unit or
something like that and you integrated
bills in my pipeline and in yours and it
fails if something in the the interface
I provide to you doesn't work anymore
correct yeah yeah it's it's more it's
more like a functional test often that
then a unit test but it could in fact be
at a unit test level but I write the
test and I give it to you so we are
talking about a micro service or
service-oriented situation you know not
necessarily we've we've used it in the
cases of reference data coming down from
mainframes where
this is how we expect to receive price
information for example for a retailer
there very often as a separate system
that is used by the marketing department
when it sets prices and does promotions
and such and we expect data to come in
to say a point-of-sale system from from
that and so we read a test which says
okay you know this is what price changes
are going to look like for example and
yeah it doesn't have to be service
oriented at all it's just okay I might
be getting I might be getting an F a
file by FTP and still like in their way
in contract between two systems correct
yeah okay
understood so I looked at your slide a
little bit so another principle you have
is architect and developed for
evolvability yes most of the the lists
civilities that that you'll see it's
reliability and scalability and the
closest we really get to evolvability is
often maintainability
how easy is it for someone to come in
and understand the code but thinking
about evolvability is not just is it
easy to understand the code that is a
big part of it is the software quality
such as is the software design as the
architectural design such that it is
easy to come in and understand the
system but there are also some things
around appropriate use of abstraction
layers because there might be some some
aspect of the system that is more likely
to change and so this is basically make
evolvability a first-class principle if
you will and just like all of the other
ility x' your need for a particular
aspect of the system to be tolerant to
evolution is go is going to be different
you know the laws of physics don't
change very often so if you have some
aspect of your system that is doing
computations on the basis of the laws of
physics you don't have to worry nearly
as much about those things changing as
you do for example how your customer
might want to interact with their
information that's much more subject to
change because consumer consumer
expectations are much more volatile
and so just like my security
characteristics or my performance
characteristics might be different my
need for evolvability
is different across a system and and you
want that to be a first-class principle
and when you're thinking about how you
how you're going to actually implement
the solution to a particular problem so
one way I can think of for to develop
for availability is pair programming
because you share knowledge is that one
of them you would think of or know the
others that that is part of it it's not
just the shared knowledge though it is
as much when when I'm writing code and
we're we're pairing on code you eat
individual is bringing their their
particular perspective to it and so
there may be things that I've you know
I've got something in my head and you've
got a different way of looking at it and
or a different vulnerability that you
might be thinking about in terms of
potential change points and so we can
have a conversation and then and that
sharing of perspectives means that we're
more likely to come up with a broader
perspective on where those where the
scope of possible change comes from in
this section you all will also talk
about metrics mm-hmm and technical depth
so how to know where you might not be so
available in the systems yes a lot of
the software metrics though that we use
really address the maintainability part
of evolvability although they often also
provide information about how how
tightly coupled different aspects of the
system are and obviously if if you have
two parts of your system that that have
a lot of cross references you don't have
clean separation it's going to be
difficult to change one part of that
without seriously impacting the other so
they're both architectural and software
metrics that address how readable some
code is how how entangled different
parts of the code or the systems are and
they allow using using software Metro
it allows us to both track how how our
system is changing over time so if we
are taking on technical that we're aware
of it and it also gives us guidance for
how to know what part of a system that
we should should focus our attention on
again I might have something that that
implements computation
based on the laws of physics well they
don't change very often now it might be
messy code but as long as the laws of
physics don't change I don't really have
to worry about that code and if it runs
fine twenty years I probably don't want
to fix it right exactly exactly that's
that's the managing the depth we
actually have a good episode and
technical depth up which is episode 224
so if you want to know more about that
topic just check out the the previous
episode so let's go to the final
principle and it's surprisingly it's
done really about software it's about
people which is Conway's law yes we're
actually hearing even more and more
about about Conway's law and informally
the way to think about Conway's law is
the the resulting architecture of the of
your system will reflect what the
organization that built that system
looks like and one one of the ways this
manifests itself if you have silos of IT
or business in reality and different
parts of your business don't communicate
well as people chances are the
integration of the systems that reflect
the functions there are not going to
integrate well because if you can't get
people to communicate with each other
you don't know well what are the
implications of the decisions that each
of those systems have has to make and so
you want to think about how your current
communication structures your current
reporting lines and the level of
dysfunction potentially between
organizations how that might impact your
system and so the punchline really is
yeah if you don't want your system to
look like your organization you better
change your organization because that is
how the system is going to look
regardless of a hard
try that organizational imprint will be
there on your system so the idea is if
you want to if you want to have people
separated by function it's like business
function rather than by bilayer you
better group the teams around the
function and not by I have a database
team I have a front-end team alright yes
how does that help was a vulnerability
well the it's it's more if if you think
about your organization and what are the
potential changes that might help occur
in how your system needs to behave if I
have rigid silos and all of my customer
data is locked up you know managed by my
customer care department but my supply
chain is locked up in my logistics
department and then all of a sudden they
say well wait a minute I want on my
online system for someone who's a
customer to be able to look at what's
the status of their order but that's
locked up in the logistic system and
having having silos around those things
means it's probably going to be very
different difficult for a system that
lives in the customer care part of my
business to get information out of the
logistics and so by by breaking down the
barriers between different parts of the
business as those needs change as those
departments need to work together
differently to support a different flow
through my enterprise assets we need the
different parts of that organization to
cooperate to allow that to happen and so
by breaking down those those silos
within the business you can have
different parts of the system interact
that hadn't interacted before you do get
a similar thing from the technical side
as well you don't want people at the
database layer or who are touching the
database only making decisions that are
right for the data layer because there
are other parts of the system that have
to access that data and so you want that
level of cooperation amongst the various
functional teams so that they understand
okay if I make this decision of the
about the data this is the impact that
it's going to have on the various system
functions does that mean that if I'm a
database expert I lose my job no not at
all
not not at all and it's interesting one
of the things that we do try to push as
agile Asst is you want people to be more
Poli skilled there are certain database
functions that we expect all developers
to be able to do there are certain
database problems that are complex
enough that you need a true database
specialist that doesn't mean that you
want that true database specialist to
also do all the grunge very simple
database work that that you know 80% of
the developers should be able to do just
fine it isn't there's no role for
specialists but how that specialist
interacts with the other teams is going
to be different all right so let's
reiterate on all the principles so you
have them at one so we have the last
responsible moment we have architect for
testability we have passwords law we
have architect and developed for a
vulnerability and we have finally
Conway's law okay I remember you shared
some techniques for doing that as
examples shall we start with database
refactoring yes we already had an
episode on this which is episode 186 on
agile database development mmm-hmm so if
you want to know more listen to that
episode but can you in one cent explain
what you mean by that and why it helps
well by it as I said earlier that the
early view was you have to do your
entire data model upfront before you can
start any kind of development and this
approach to evolutionary databases takes
into account the challenges that you
have if you have a database in
production that now you're you want to
change in some ways and it looks at how
do I do a refactoring on a database just
like a code refactoring is is one very
simple change that's easy to test and
easy to maintain
havior well there's a there's a series
of refactorings that you can do on
databases and the refactoring is the
actual change to the database as well as
what kind of migrations might I have to
run to move production data from the old
to the new and then of course you change
our code and so you decompose all of the
different changes you're making to your
database into these simple refactorings
that are much easier to test in
isolation and then you just compose them
yeah so so what it essentially means is
rather than having one big SQL script to
set up my database I have a number of
them correct maybe 20 and they will
step-by-step set up the database and I
can also deploy them yes is the rest
okay then we have continuous delivery
also mentioned in show 121 right so the
reason continuous delivery is important
for evolutionary architecture is you
want to be able to to safely change your
system and deploy something new into
production and continuous delivery is
all about making deployments boring so
you can celebrate the features and not
the fact that you didn't crash the
system into production and one aspect of
evolutionary archit architecture is you
are going to most likely be deploying
more frequently and sometimes making
some pretty fundamental changes to for
example what your technology stack might
look like and continuous delivery
provides the approach to making changes
like that as risk-free as possible yeah
and it allows you to kind of evolve your
fitness function faster because you get
the feedback if you have the right fit
and fitness function absolutely ernia
yeah so the last one we want to talk
about is micro services where we had
three episodes by now which is one to
ten to thirteen and to 16 I'm going to
link all of them in the show notes so
you don't have to time so micro services
means I decompose my application into a
bunch of small services why does that
help was evolutionary architecture
because it allows you to over time
compose those smaller services to
deliver diff
pieces of a business logic it also
allows you potentially to swap out an
implementation of a particular function
with a completely new implementation
because you were thinking about you're
architecting in a microservices
architecture to have these these
different again small c components or
micro-services in your system you were
thinking about what those boundaries
should look like and because you're
enforcing those boundaries you can move
things around you know and you can
replace individual parts with something
different that has potentially different
architectural characteristics as an
example so there is this this notion of
design for replacement rather than for
reuse yes yeah all right so what is the
trouble or let me phrase it maybe
differently so given I'm in a project
which runs since three years and we
started with a bit big upfront design
mm-hmm is it still possible to start
with evolutionary architecture yes you
can gradually introduce abstraction
layers that will allow you to change
some of those architectural
characteristics but when you're starting
from a legacy system probably the most
important of those architectural
principles since you've made a lot of
the decisions already worrying about the
last responsible moment is perhaps less
important but you still want to think
about what do I have to do to make this
system as evolvable as process as
possible you want to start disentangling
different parts of your system you want
to identify where the hotspots where I
have too much architectural dependence
within a particular aspect of my system
and oh by the way if that's something
that's changing a lot or something that
is that tends to be buggy then I'm going
to want to focus my effort they're
thinking about architecting for
evolvability as well as for testability
because as I said earlier thinking about
testability actually gives you those
kinds of clean interface points that
make it easier to evolve different parts
of your system independently and what is
the the meta when I'm buying software so
is there still some some room for it or
do I have to stick with everything it's
a little more difficult when you're
doing packet selection although you do
want to still look at how easy is it for
me to redeploy this system is it
possible for me to incrementally
configure this is it possible to put the
critical parts of any customization in
source control so there are a lot of
things particularly around continuous
delivery that that would affect my
packet selection and then also thinking
about how easy or difficult it is to
test the resulting bit behavior that
you're getting out of that package when
you think about a package that is only
fulfilling one function out of the
broader system then you want to start to
look at how easy is it to get the right
kind of separation to set up the
contract test to get the communication
the messaging set up in such a way that
it respects things like pastels law okay
so I I still applied the principles in
the software selection yes alright so
when I was at university my professors
told me that good architecture means I
can reuse my code everywhere it's a
wonderful goal but the problem is very
often to have that code be reusable you
have to be able to predict how somebody
is going to want to use it and sometimes
that's clear you know if I if I'm
working on something quite simple you
calendar functionality well we kind of
know how people like to use calendars
they want to be able to schedule
recurring appointments and they want it
to be tolerant of daylight savings time
and all of times don't changes and and
and all of those kinds of things so it's
not too difficult to come up with a
component that has a robust set of
calendar features trying to speculate
how your customers are going to want to
personalize their information five years
from now how are you going to know and
so when we think about reuse from an
evolutionary perspective it's more when
I see instances of reuse I can analyze
them and say okay what can i abstract
from these different actual
usage patterns which is going to give me
some guidance and how within my
organization people want to use this
data and then I can make something
that's reusable but I'm I'm making it
reusable on the basis of real
information rather than trying to guess
what's gonna happen in the future so at
the art of evolution and architecture is
to know what I know and to know what I
not don't know and try to make as few
decisions as possible on the basis of
things that you don't know okay so my
last question so there is no free lunch
so what are the costs and the downsides
of evolutional architecture well you
can't get things wrong if you make a
particular decision you might if you
would thought about everything if you
taken everything into account at the
beginning you might have done something
different you might have been able to
find a more efficient architecture you
might have been able to put something in
place that you could take advantage of
the problem with that is yes if if you
get it right you can probably save
yourself some time but what's the
probability that you're gonna get it
right and therein lies the problem and
so there are some some situations where
maybe you do know more about how
something's going to happen something
that maybe corresponds to a regulatory
framework and because the way
government's work you know that
regulatory framework is not going to
change over the next two years or five
years well if you know what that
framework looks like you can make more
decisions up front because you have less
probability that that thing is going to
change out from under you and that is
going to be more efficient because if
you're taking advantage of more
additional information you won't have to
you know potentially build abstraction
layers or you won't have to redo
something because you learned something
that maybe you could have known if you
thought about it so there are
inefficiencies the that are built into
supporting this level of evolve evolve
ability because you might develop more
layers correct Winston's okay and and
and of course a micro service
architecture is more work in the
beginning
yeah and one onus yes yes because you
have a lot more to monitor you and and
you have to think about problems that
you don't have to worry about the
permutations of failures when you have
independent micro-services running in
different processes versus a monolith
when I'm in a model if I know that
either
the entire thing is alive or the entire
thing is dead in general that's not true
and microservices architecture and if if
my service is looking at five different
services well any combination of those
five may be unavailable so that's an
that's that's all these permutations of
failures that I have to think about
whereas I don't have to worry about that
if it's a monolith if it's all in the
same process then we're either all
working or all not without anything in
between okay so that's all from my set
is there something you would like to add
from your side well one of the things
though that we're looking at doing is
trying to get more information out there
about evolutionary architecture there's
the book on micro-services the book on
continuous delivery the book on an
evolutionary databases but there really
isn't anything out there that really
talks about how to do evolutionary
architecture and what it means and what
some of these pitfalls are and that's
something that over the over the next
several months I'm hoping to address so
hopefully you'll start to see some
articles and and some other web
resources that will that will provide
guidance in this area okay that's very
nice so is there any resources you would
like to point people to now there's
actually very little except I speak on
evolutionary architecture and agile and
enterprise architecture a fair amount
and there are there of several videos
out there that's available but we'll be
posting some of these things both on the
thought Works website in it Rebecca
Parsons comm yeah I will make sure to
keep the su rated website updated so
where can people find out more about you
personally I do have a website which is
currently very inactive Rebecca Parsons
comm and of course there's lots of
information on the thought Works website
and my twitter handle is at Rebecca
Parsons okay perfect
so thank you very much all the
information mentioned this episode will
will be in the shown on thanks Rebecca
for being on the show thank you very
much it was a pleasure
I would like before we close to remind
our listeners that you can comment on
this episode on se - reggienet
you can also send an email to the team
via team at SU radio dotnet we have
twitter at SU radio and we are linked in
Google+ and Facebook all of them
software engineering radio so really let
us know what you think we like to hear
your feedback we like to hear who we
should invite next so with that I thank
you for listening and good bye
[Music]
thanks for listening
SC radio an educational program brought
to you by I Triple E software magazine
for more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radio name to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
Twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on link
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
you